<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pronostication [sic] for the yere of our Lord God M.CCCCC.xliiii practysed by the right expert doctour in astronomy and phisycke Maister Cornelys Scute ...</title>
            <author>Scute, Cornelys.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1544</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18545</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 508.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1475</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20185954</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20185954</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23738</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18545)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23738)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1700:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pronostication [sic] for the yere of our Lord God M.CCCCC.xliiii practysed by the right expert doctour in astronomy and phisycke Maister Cornelys Scute ...</title>
                  <author>Scute, Cornelys.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted at London in the Olde Bayly in Sayntpoulchres paryssh by Rychard Lant for Rychard Grafton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1544?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Cu[m] privilegio ad imprimendu[m] solu[m]"--P. [46].</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F³.</note>
                  <note>"Formerly STC 22129"--STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: signatures A3 and D4 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Almanacs, English.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23738:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23738:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A prono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtication for the yere of our <hi>LORD GOD</hi> M. CCCCC. xliiii</p>
            <p>Practyſed by the right expert Doctour in Aſtronomy and phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſycke Maiſter Cornelys Scute reſydent in Bridges in the wolfe ſtrete.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23738:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:23738:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the Reder.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I begin to come to my principall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this yere I haue taken in hand fyrſt to rebuke the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>heme of a certayne Pronoſticatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the yere of our lorde a thouſand fyue hundreth xliii. laſt paſt / made by one maiſter Henry ſwart / of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperne: which dyd his vttermoſt to make the people beleue that the ſcy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence of Aſtronomye is nothynge worth / but euyll: and the ſame is alſo a gret hyndraunce to the helth of mans body / and that ſome Phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſytions do aſcribe the cauſe of ſyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes (agaynſt all reaſon) to come by the heauens / Starres / Plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / Eclipſes and Comettes. &amp; cet. Sayeng / that if ſo be that this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueliſſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng had not ben taken
<pb facs="tcp:23738:3"/> vp / many one ſhuld yet haue lyued longer. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundyng by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noſtication to all Phiſitions / that they ſhuld leue this connyng of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomye / alonely to practyſe the right bokes of ſurgery. And alſo more iniury hath he done agaynſt this excellent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng / which were to longe here to expreſſe. Now to come to euery poynt afore wrytten only to teſtifye / that the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of Aſtronomy is nedefall / &amp; principally for Phiſytions to my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter by to them that haue nede of it / for to helpe and cure the body of man. So it is of a truth / that Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates / whoſe auctorotye and ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellency in ſurgery he can not deny by reaſon / all this ſayenge in the Greke tonge / now tourned in to Englyſſhe: who that ſhall gyue himſelf
<pb facs="tcp:23738:3"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing of the ſicknes ſhalbe of vomy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge coller or wamblynge of the mawe. All ſuch lyke ſycknes ſhall be apte to take all colde congealed maters: for as moche as the mone is not ſhadoed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any other good Planetes / the man ſhall dye in the firſt quadra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / that is to wyt / whan the mone ſhall come the thyrd ſyne folowyng: But if the mone be ſha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doed with any good planets / than ſhall the man ouer comme it in the firſt quadrant: that is to wyt / with in. vii. or. viii. days after. Alſo Gallene ſayth in the ende of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me boke i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this maner: that a good Phiſytion oughte to haue euer in his remembraunce the ſcyence of Aſtronomy / and that with all his endeuer ought to enquyre the day and tyme whan the ſycknes began
<pb facs="tcp:23738:4"/> or what tyme the hurte or fall / or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch lyke chaunſed / and muſt loke than after what ſorte the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens &amp; ſtarres ſtode at that tyme / conſydring that here in this world chaunſeth nothing / but by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement of the heuen aboue.</p>
            <p>Alſo the gret lerned man Hermes Termegiſcus / ſpeketh after this maner: A good Phiſytion whiche ſhall helpe a man by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng / muſt beholde the conſtitution or inclina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / with the ſtarres / how they agre togither. Alſo Ariſtotle ſayth / in the fyrſt boke and ſecond chapiter. Alſo Auicen <hi>Doctrina. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. cap, vii, Secundum res celeſtes &amp; res terreſtres eueniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ille uero que res ſecuntur celeſtes, ſunt ſicut ea que ſtella<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſa accidunt, eſt enim cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>multe ex ſtellis in uno coniungitur</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:23738:4"/> 
               <hi>loco et coniungitur ſoli, et prouenit ex hoc califactio multa.</hi> Item Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homeron / Abinzoer / an excellent Phiſytion ſayth. <hi>libro primo cap. vii. in epilepſia paroxiſmi: Fieri co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſueuerunt ex operatione ſuper cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtium corporum que a deo uiuo &amp; ue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ro parfectionem &amp; influentiam habe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re &amp; reſipere ſciuntur.</hi> To this he putteth to thuetoritie of Arnoldus <hi>de uilla noua</hi> and Raſys and other lerned Phiſytions / whoſe wordes here to declare wolde be to longe / remembryng alſo that here is wyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſed ynough agaynſt the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſayeng of the aforeſayd maiſter Henry: that the Scyence of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy is a godly connynge &amp; nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for Phiſitions to know.</p>
            <p>Item where as the aforeſayd M. Henry ſayth / that the Pronoſtica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb facs="tcp:23738:5"/> ſaye not euer trew / is made anſwere ynough by Ptolome <hi>quin to ece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenis enuntiato.</hi> And alſo by Iohan Pontanium in the coment there vpon made / And alſo <hi>in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemio libri ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ii. de rebus celeſtibꝰ.</hi> it wold be to longe to reherſe word for word in this lytell boke. Item this M. Henry ſayth in the ſame Prouoſticatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (without diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) of a chylde of. xii. yeres. ſlepyng na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turally / goyng and ſtandyng / that within two yeres had neither eten nor dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ken / ſayeng that euery one learned in that naturall connynge ought to applye them ſelues to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke a naturall anſwer or reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there vnto / the whiche he hoped to do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her face: whiche is a ſtraunge vnderſtandyng to gyue there vnto a naturall reaſon / which is befall
<pb facs="tcp:23738:5"/> contrary agaynſt all nature / folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynge the ſentence of Hipocrates <hi>in Aphoris.</hi> 14. where he ſayth that it is agaynſt goddes commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to gyue confydence to the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noſtication: ſo ſay I that it is true that we ſhall not beleue it ſo fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully as the word of god in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell or by the prophetes which can not lye in no wyſe / but muſt be eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they be ſpoken <hi>iuxta illud, Mat. xxiiii.</hi> but it may be lauful to gyue ſuch credence there vnto as we gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue to phiſycke &amp; other. We none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe doo diſpoſe than the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſygnes do declare / beholdi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g that the workes be wonderous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding all iudgementes of nature. And ye ſhall vnderſtand that I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue not ſayd this before mencyoned not in deriſyon or to ſhame the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd
<pb facs="tcp:23738:6"/> maiſter Henry / but alon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for his vnlauful opinion that he had to argue vpon agaynſt thexel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent connyng of Aſtronomy.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The Operation of the foure Eclypſes of this yere.</head>
               <p>WE ſhall haue in this Lepe yere / foure Eclypſes / that is to wyt / thre of the mone and one of the ſonne.</p>
               <div n="1" type="eclipse">
                  <p>The fyrſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyppes of the Mone ſhall befall the tenth day of Ianuary at vi. of the clocke before none / which ſhal be of. xii. poyntes &amp; xlvi. mynutes / ſo that the Mone ſhall abyde hole darkened xli min. and ſhall conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue her Eclyppes thre houres and xxviii. mi. The Mone ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Northweſt / with hye exal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacion
<pb facs="tcp:23738:6"/> aboue the earth / in the myd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of the Eclyppes / and ſhall not as yet be all about lyght whan it goeth downe. Mars / Iupiter and Saturnus ſhall ſtande aboute the ſonth ſoutheaſt. Venus and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curius ſhall aſcende in the hygheſt whan the darkeneſſe of the Mone begynneth to vanyſſhe away: they ſhall haue for their aſcendent / the fyrſt degre of capricorn in the myd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of heuen / in the xxvi. degre of libra. The Mone ſhalbe in the .vii. houſe of heuen / and ſhal begyn the operation of this Eclyppes about Auguſt / as Ptolome ſayth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="eclipse">
                  <head>The ſecond Eclyppes.</head>
                  <p>THe ſecond Eclyppes ſhalbe of the Sonne / the .xxiiii. daye of Ianuary at viii. a clocke xxiii. min. before none / and ſhallbe
<pb facs="tcp:23738:7"/> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. poyntes / almoſt. xvii. min, ſo that all the hole Sonne ſaue a ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tell ſhalbe darkened. The Sonne ſhall ſtand ſouth ſoutheſt with the mone / which ſhall ſtand right vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sonne / ſo that in our ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone if ſhal hynder and take away the brightneſſe of the Son: which Eclyppes and alſo other Eclypſes before goyng we ſhall well &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytly ſe if that ye ſe the mone or the ſonne. And if caſe be that through darkeneſſe of the wether we ſhuld not ſe the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne or the mone / yet the Eclyppes ſhall be neuer the leſſe if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhuld not ſe it. The Eclyppes ſhall haue before his aſcendent the xii. degre of Aries. Venus ſhalbe in the vi. degre of capricorne right ſouth / ſyttyng in the myddes of he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, Iupiter &amp; Saturnus ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:23738:7"/> in the eyght houſe about the ſouth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weſt: all the ſeuen planetes ſhall as than be aboue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erth / that is to wyt / thre in the eight houſe / two in the tenthe houſe / and two in the xi. houſe / which ſhalbe wonderfull &amp; of great miſtery. Out of theſe iiii. Eclipſes ſhalbe brought forth wonderfull maters / as we ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſe here after. Mars ſhall be in the Eclyppes of the Sonne in the houſe of death, <hi>in Scorpio. in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria domo, gaudio ꝓprio. &amp; propria triplicitate.</hi> Iupiter ſhalbe <hi>in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prio caſu,</hi> betwene Saturne and Mars / in the eyght houſe of death alſo.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="eclipse">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Here after foloweth the thyrde Eclyppes of the Moone.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23738:8"/>
                  <p> THe thyrd Eclyppes ſhalbe of the mone / &amp; ſhalbe the fourth day of Iuly viii. a clocke. xxi mi. after none / and ſhall be of xvii. poyntes &amp; xv. my. ſo that the mone ſhalbe hole darke i, houre &amp; a halfe &amp; ſhall endure longer than the firſt and ſhall be almoſt hole darkened whan it ſhall ryſe in the eſt: ſo that it ſhall ſeme to be a wonderfull ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. Saturnus and Iupiter ſhall ſyt togyther in the ſouth / &amp; Mars beneth the ſoutheaſt / Mercurius in the weſt northweſt. The aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſhalbe the viii. degre of aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius. The Son ſhalbe in the viii. houſe. The operation of this ſhall begyn incontynently after that the Eclippes ſhalbe paſſed / and ſhall fall very ſtronge at that tyme.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="eclipse">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23738:8"/>
                  <head>A fourth Eclyppes.</head>
                  <p>THe fourth Eclyppes is of the Moone / &amp; ſhalbe the. xxix, day of December / at. vi. a clocke &amp;. xx. myn. before noone / and ſhalbe of xiiii. poyntes. xviii. myn. Than ſhal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moone ſit about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> northweſt before the day / and ſhall go downe all blacke &amp; darkened. The moone ſhalbe an hole houre darke and. iii myn. and ſhall endure from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge to thende thre houres &amp; xxxvi. mynu. and ſhall haue the ſelf ſame aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Iunii. mediu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>li.</hi> and alſo <hi>occaſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> with gods / alſo thother houſes of the heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhalbe euen as the heuens were at the tyme of the other foreſayd eclypſis / which ſhal be a wonderous matter / as is well knowen to all aſtronomers. Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Marcurius ſhall ſyt bothe ſoutheaſt / in the xii. hous about the
<pb facs="tcp:23738:9"/> erth. Saturne ſhall ſyt in the ſouth ſoutheaſt / and ſo forth all the other planettes ſhalbe vnder the erth / the aſcendent ſhalbe the fyrſt degre of Capricornus / in the myddes of the heuens / in the rxvi, degre of Libra and ſo forth as it is in the foreſayd Eclipſes</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of ſyckneſſes that ſhall reygne this yere.</head>
               <p>PAruſing the ſignes made vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the calculations of heuens / the tymes of the foure Eclipſis afore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſayd / I fynde that this yere ſhalbe apte to great burnyng and feruent ſyckneſſes / of the which many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall dye / yt that the mercyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of god do not helpe: It is to be doubted of great deth. There ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:23738:9"/> reygne moche payne in the heade / in the throte / in the ſydes / with bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge agues / and ſo forth. Thoſe that hath Scorpio / Piſces / or Can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cer in the myddes of heuens with one aſpect quadrant / or the oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saturne or Mars ſhal be this yrre ſore vexed with ſyckneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes / comonly with the foreſayd tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitye / or of ſuche lyke humours or matters as the aforeſayd tripli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citye is gyuynge and bryngynge forth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of all growynge thynges</head>
               <p>AL thynges that by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of Mars and Venus are aſcribed vnto / and are vnder theyr protection / ſhal proſpere well
<pb facs="tcp:23738:10"/> this yere / and encreaſe to the great auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage of the people. They may ſtande in ieopardye in the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of Apryll / and in the ende of Marche / but they ſhal ꝓſpere well agayne in the buddynge tyme / but thoſe that haue Iupiter and Sol to their protector / ſhall haue moche hynderau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in their buddyng / how be it there ſhalbe ſuccour done fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other quarters / ſo that they ſhall not be very deare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of the foure ceaſons of the yere / </head>
               <div n="winter" type="season">
                  <head>and fyrſt of Wynter.</head>
                  <p>WHat tyme the foure ſeaſons of the yere begyn I haue ſhewed vnto the people ynough in tymes paſt / ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ought now to know that them ſelues / wherfore it is no nede to ſpeake more of that / but go
<pb facs="tcp:23738:10"/> vnto the properties and inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the foure quarters of the yeare / than muſt I fyrſt make mencion of the Wynter / which is vntemperat / and than of the two Eclypſis / the one of the Sonne / &amp; the other of the Moone / whiche ſhalbe in Ianuary nexte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge very vntemperate / with greate tempeſtes of wyndes / and ſhalbe apt to froſt ynough / du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge longe / but not ſo ſore as the laſt wynter was. Gouernours of landes / cytyes / &amp; caſtels muſt than take good hede / and weapon them agaynſt treaſon / for there ſhall be many ſecretly conſpyred / and than ſhal reygne vnreaſonable ſortes of ſyckneſſes / and in ſome places pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilens in generall / with dyuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers / Wherfore I wyll ſpeake no more of that.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Lent" type="season">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23738:11"/>
                  <head>Of the Lent ſeaſon.</head>
                  <p>IN the Lent ſeaſon ſhal there be moch rumoure and newes of warres. And there ſhall as tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> raygne many new diſeaſes which ſhalbe very harde for Phiſytions and Surgyons to cure. And it ſhall be in the begynnynge colde / with raynes hayle and ſnowe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="summer" type="season">
                  <head>Of the Somer.</head>
                  <p>THe Somer begynneth the xi day of Iune at ten of the clocke at night / and ſhall haue for his aſcendent the tenth degre of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarius in the myddes of heuens. The fyrſt degree of Sagittarius and Iupiter ſhallbe in the nyenth houſe / and Mars in the leue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th / the
<pb facs="tcp:23738:11"/> Sonne in the fyfth houſe / and ſhal be after her ſignification enclyned to great bloude ſhedynge and alſo to great vexations / ſeditions and warres, alſo it ſemeth that thorow thexpectation of Iupiter &amp; Mars with the ſextile aſpect / Spirituall perſones / as the byſſhop of Rome &amp; other may well go aboute to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n appoyntement / but they ſhal no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> bringe it to paſſe nor to none ef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fecte / and alſo with great faruent and hote ſickneſſes ſhal they be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected / whiche ſhall come of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward partes with gret feuers and paynes in the head &amp; alſo peſtilens</p>
               </div>
               <div n="harvest" type="season">
                  <head>Of the Harueſt.</head>
                  <p>¶ The Harueſt this yere ſhalbe ſomewhat warmer and dryer than
<pb facs="tcp:23738:12"/> it hath ben in tymes paſt / in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge with moche dew / in the ende with moche rayne / and ſhalbe wyndy among / with a lytel rayne. There ſhall than reygne many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues and quarteyns / with paynes in the heed / in ſome places with pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtilens: of the collycke ſhall many people be infected.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of the xii. monethes and their quarters.</head>
               <div n="January" type="month">
                  <head>Ianuary.</head>
                  <p>The fyrſt quarter the ſecond day at two a clocke before noone / many dark days / with wyndes &amp; froſtes. The full moone the x. daye at vi. a clocke before none / and than is the eclippes of the mone / with ſnow in ſome places. The laſt quarter the xvii. day at vi. a clocke after none, variable / with froſtes / rymes and
<pb facs="tcp:23738:12"/> wyndes. The new mone the xxiiii day at ix. a clocke xxii. myn. before none / than is the clips of the Son / with colde / dankiſſh &amp; a lytel froſt. The fyrſt quarter the xxxi. day at x. a clock after none / moyſt &amp; colde.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="February" type="month">
                  <head>February.</head>
                  <p>The full mone the viii. day at x. a clock xxvi. mi. after none / winde and variable. The laſt quarter the xvi. day at one a clocke before none variable with rayne &amp; ſnowe. The new mone the xxii, day at x. a clock and iiii. mynu. at after none / ſome tyme fowle wether.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="March" type="month">
                  <head>Marche,</head>
                  <p>The fyrſt quarter / the fyrſt daye at vi, a clocke after none / as before wyth certayne fayre dayes. The full mone / the ix. day. xii. a clocke at nyght / varyable / tolde / wyndye
<pb facs="tcp:23738:13"/> ſomtyme fayre wethrr. The laſt quarter the .xvi. daye at ſeuen of the clocke in the mourning / accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the ceaſon.</p>
                  <p>The new mone the xxiii. day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none. ii. of the clocke at night varyable with wynde and rayne. The fyrſt quarter the xxxi. daye at one of the clocke after none / Colde wyndye &amp; ſomtyme fayre wether.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="April" type="month">
                  <head>Apryll.</head>
                  <p>The full mone the ſeuenth day at ten of the clocke xxx. mynutes at after noone / reaſonable with colde ſomtyme varyable. The laſt quar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the fourthe daye at one a clocke after noone / ſomtyme rayne. The new moone the xxii. daye at two of the clocke and. xx. mynutes before none / ſomtyme drye and wyndye.
<pb facs="tcp:23738:13"/> The fyrſt quarter the xxx. daye at v, a clocke after none / acordyng to the ceaſon with a lytell rayne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="May" type="month">
                  <head>May.</head>
                  <p>The full mone the ſeuenth daye at vi, of the clocke. xlviii. mynutes before noone / throughout as before The laſt quarter / the one &amp; thirtye daye at nyne of the clocke at after noone / almoſt as before. The new mone the xxi. day at v, of the clocke the ſyxth mynute at after none / va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryable. The fyrſt quarter the xxix. daye at ſeuen of the clocke at after noone / ſomtyme wyndye and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyſſhe with hote and fayre dayes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="June" type="month">
                  <head>Here after foloweth the moneth of Iune.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23738:14"/>
                  <p> The full mone / the fyfth day at ten a clocke. xliii. mi. after noone / hote / varyable / with lyghtnynge. The laſt quarter the xxi. day at vii a clocke in the mornyng / varyable with heate. The new mone the .xx. day at eyght a clocke before none / fayre ſomtyme wynd and moyſty The fyrſt quarter the xxviii. daye at vi. a clocke before none / almoſt as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="July" type="month">
                  <head>Iulius.</head>
                  <p>The full mone / the fourth daye at viii. a clocke xxi. min. after none and than is the clippes of the mone metely fayre wether. The laſt q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xi. day. viii. at after none / ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nme rayne &amp; temperate. The new mone the third day at ten a clocke xxxvi. min. after noone / accordyng to the ceaſone / ſomwhat variable. The
<pb facs="tcp:23738:14"/> firſt quarter the xxvii. daye at. ii. a clocke after none / almoſt as before</p>
               </div>
               <div n="August" type="month">
                  <head>Auguſt.</head>
                  <p>The full mone / the third daye at. iiii. a clocke after noone / ſomty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me moyſty. The laſt quarter the .x. daye xi. of the clocke before noone variable. The new mone the xviii. day / one a clock after none / moiſte with wyndes / ſomtymes ſonſhyne The firſt quarter / the xxv. daye at one of the clocke after none / almoſt as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="September" type="month">
                  <head>Septembre.</head>
                  <p>The full mone the fyrſt daye at one a clocke and. xl. mi. after none wyndy / ſomtyme moiſt and colde The laſt quarter the, ix. day at, v. clock before none / cold / wynd / and rayne with the ſonne ſhynynge.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23738:15"/>
                  <p> The new mone the ſeuentyne day at two of the clocke the xl. mynute. before Noone / wyndye / ſomtyme reaſonable. The fyrſt quarter the xxiii. day at two of the clocke / the fourth mynute afore none / myſtye with deaw / wynde and rayne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="October" type="month">
                  <head>October.</head>
                  <p>The full mone the fyrſt day at ii. of the clocke before none / moyſt with wynde, The laſt quarter the nyenth day at one of the clocke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noone / colde / with rayne and darke dayes. The new moone the xvi, daye at thre of the clocke &amp; xxx. mynutes at afternoone / varyable with wynd. The fyrſt quarter the xxiii. daye at nyne a clocke before noone / ſomtyme rayne / colde / and wyndy / and ſomtyme otherwyſe. The full Moone the xxx. day at. v. a clocke</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2+ pages">
                  <desc>〈2… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:23738:15"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:23738:16"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:23738:16"/>
               <p>throughout all the worlde / princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally in our realme here / with va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riaunce / ſedition / and open warre / many men ſhalbe ſpoyled &amp; ſlayne / houſes / caſtels / and cytyes ſhalbe taken / brent and deſtroyed / the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple ſhalbe without mercy or pytye. The countreys beynge vnder the protection of Aries / as Fraunce / Englande / and a parte of Dutche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lande / with hole Denmarke / ſhall haue moch to do. And I ſe not / nor I fynde not / after myne opynyon / that theſe warres and variaunces ſhalbe appeaſed / how be it in the Eclippes of the Moone the fourth daye of Iuly / Iupiter is lodged euen aboute the myddes of the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens / for Mars beyng in the clips of the Moone in Ianuary aſited in the tenth houſe in the hyeſt ſeate of
<pb facs="tcp:23738:17"/> the heuens. Italye / Lumbardye / Pyemont / Naples / Poullye / Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labre / Sicilie / Corphen / Sardayn Mynorq<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Molto / Matorq<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Spayne Portyngale / Hungary / Albanye / Poole / Boheme / &amp; ſo forth a great part of Aſia and Af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rica / ſhalbe all in trouble and warre / we may wel trymble at the newes that we ſhall here dayly / as well of the Turkes and ſaraſyns as of the Chriſtians A bodyes heare of his heade may ſomtyme ſtande vpryght for feare of theſe newe tydynges / which we ſhall dayly here of. The feates of warre and the victory ſhall ſtande dyuers tymes variable / ſo that in one countrey there ſhall be cytyes and townes won / and in an other loſt agayne. Let vs pray vnto god earneſtly / that he may faſten the
<pb facs="tcp:23738:17"/> princes hartes / &amp; turne it to peace / contrary to ther poſitions and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of the heuens.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of Phillip the kynge of Spayne.</head>
               <p>PHillip the ſonne of Charles kyng of Spayne / who ſhalbe of age in the yere of our lorde god M. v. C. xliiii. xvii. yeres old / and he hath in his reuolution this yere the firſt degre of Piſces / for his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent is in the fyrſt houſe / Lun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the fourth / Iupiter / Sol / Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus / and Marcurius / al <hi>in octaua, pars fortune in nona,</hi> Saturnus <hi>in ſexta,</hi> ſoo that his fygure this yere is enclyned to be almoſt as it was in his byrthe / after the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the planets / whiche ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:23738:18"/> a wonderfull token / and ſhall be through Mars / beynge about the aſcendent / and he ſhall be this yere very liberall to thoſe that employ themſelues vnto hym in feates of weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / and ſhalbe hymſelfe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous deſyrous to warre / for to vaynquyſh his fathers ennemyes / ſo that he through the gyfte of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune ſhalbe very ſtrong / as well by the helpe and aſſiſtens of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualtye as of the temporaltye / and ſhall gete great victory / and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere by warre. Saturnus beyng in the ſixth houſe thretneth his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty ſomwhat with ſycknes of his body <hi>ex humoribus craſſis,</hi> and alſo <hi>calcuioſis ex materia viſcida,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he muſt take good hede of hym ſelfe / &amp; that with good aduyſement the more bycauſe that Sol and Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piter
<pb facs="tcp:23738:18"/> are in the eyght houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of thr Emperours maieſtye.</head>
               <p>CHarles the fyfthe Emperour of Rome / after the fygure of his reuolution of this yere. M. v. hundreth and. xliiii. ſhall haue for his aſcendent the xi. degre of Leo / and in the myddes of heuens Aries <hi>domu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Martis cum caſum Saturnus</hi> whiche at the tyme of his birth had a lucky fygure of the heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / ſo that Iupiter / Sol / Marcurius <hi>pars for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tune</hi> and Venus were all <hi>in domo ſecunda,</hi> whiche ſhall this yere be ſo ſore mynded to warre as euer he was in his lyfe / and ſhall through Aries beynge in the tenth houſe / be counſeylled, <hi>aſpectu trino &amp; ſextile,</hi> of good planets / and they be therin
<pb facs="tcp:23738:19"/> very lucky / &amp; ſhall haue great vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory and proſpere gretly, Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the leſſe / bycauſe that Mars is in the fyfth houſe / &amp; Saturnus and Iupiter in the fourthe houſe / it is greatly to be coniectured / that he ſhal haue ſome gret thing agaynſt him / ſo that his mynde ſhalbe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten troubled / but yet he ſhall ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all at length / through Sol beynge Lorde of thaſcendent / but not without gret bloude ſhedyng of many men / bycauſe that the lord of thaſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dent is lodged in the viii. houſe which is the houſe of death But through Venus beyng in the ſyxth houſe / there might chaunce ſome inconuenyence of ſyckneſſe vnto him / how be it / it ſhall notte hynder him. And alſo he ſhalbe in many feates of warre victoriouſe / 
<pb facs="tcp:23738:19"/> and ſhalbe feared ſore of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes / whiche ſhall bere vnto him ſecretly a good hert.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the kyng of Englandes Maieſtye.</head>
               <p>HEnry the eight / king of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande / who was .lii. yeres olde in the moneth of Iune laſt paſt / hauynge in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolution of this yere Saturnus in the Aſcendent of Virgo / in the myddes of heuen. And his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtye ſhall bere him ſelfe wiſely this yere in all his affayres / and ſhall be alſo lucky in his ſettynge for the through the excellency of Fortune beyng in the myddes of the heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with Iuppiter and Venus in the ix, houſe: wherfore he ſhall trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe in money &amp; gyftes beyng very
<pb facs="tcp:23738:20"/> lyberall. It ſhall be good to ſerue him this yere / by cauſe that Mercu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rius is lorde of the myddes of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens. In warres he ſhall alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpere &amp; haue great fortune / bycauſe that Luna is in the viii. houſe / wel infourmed <hi>aſpectu ſextill</hi> of other good Planetes. His Realme ſhall proſpere in the feates of merchun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſe / and be fortunate. And he ſhal haue more honoure this yere / than he hath had in many yeres paſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpecyall loue of his ſubiectes. And ſhalbe in the lent very earneſt for ſome cauſes that hath ben longe in his here for to bryng it to a good ende / effecte and purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:23738:20"/>
               <head>¶ Of the Frenche Kynge,</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rauncys / the French kig &amp; fyrſt of that name / who is in the moneth of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember next commynge. l. yeres olde. After the reuolution of this yeare he ſhall oftentymes be heuy of chere / and ſhall haue great loſſe in his dominion / &amp; ſhall haue but lytell good lucke in the feates of warre. Some of his gentylles ſhall ſecretly departe from hym / he ſhal do his vttermoſt by one thyrd perſon to entreate for peace / but it ſhall not preuayle / his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey ſhal be ſore vexed euery where / he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo enclined to fal in to a great ſyck<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and dredefull / Mars fortunate is to hym lodged in an vnfortuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble houſe / hauyng very euyll aſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes
<pb facs="tcp:23738:21"/> in his aſcendent &amp; in the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / wherfore he hath nede to loke wyſely aboute him &amp; his ſubiectes. In his owne par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone he wyll come to the felde / but he ſhall bere awaye lytell honoure or lucke.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <trailer>¶ Thus endeth the Pronoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation for the yere of our lord a M. v. C. xliiii and here after foloweth an Aduartyſement of Phiſycke <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:23738:21"/>
            <head>¶ An aduertyſement.</head>
            <p>PTolome ſayth in the C. xx. concluſyons / on this wyſe Enterpriſe not with iern to open any membre whan the Mone is in any Signe that hath dominion of that membre: By the which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / the Philoſopher wyl haue vs to obſerue the courſe of the Mone in pourgynge of the bodyes / by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that the operation of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne is to moyſten the bodyes, This is parceyued effectually in the greued membre that is ſubiect vnto the Sygne where in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne is vpon any day / where by it fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loweth / that it is not lefull to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that membre / as longe as the Moone is in that Sygne F. ii.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:23738:22"/>
            <head>The nature of the twelue heuenly Sygnes.</head>
            <p>The xii. heuenly Sygnes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng in vs / are lyke vnto foure ele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <head>Theſe in wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng are hote drye / fyrye and coloricke</head>
                  <item>Aries</item>
                  <item>Leo</item>
                  <item>Sagittarius</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <head>Theſe in wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng ar colde drye / earthy &amp; melancolycke.</head>
                  <item>Taurus</item>
                  <item>Uirgo</item>
                  <item>Capricornus</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <head>Theſe in wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng are moyſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yerly &amp; ſanguyne.</head>
                  <item>Gemini</item>
                  <item>Libra</item>
                  <item>Aquarius</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <head>Theſe in wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng at moiſt watry / fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</head>
                  <item>Cancer</item>
                  <item>Scorpio</item>
                  <item>Piſces</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>¶ Theſe ſygnes doth the Moone ouer ronne all within the ſpace of xxvii. dayes and the third parte of
<pb facs="tcp:23738:22"/> a day / but ſome ouerconneth them in the ſpace of a yere / that is in. C. C C xlv. days &amp; a quarter of a day</p>
            <p>It is to be noted alſo that a daye contayneth foure &amp; twenty houres and the houre xl, mynutes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>Of Phlebotony or bloud lettinge</head>
            <p>¶ In lettynge of bloude are theſe thre to be obſerued / namely the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenyent ſygnes where in the mone is / the complexion and the age of a man. The ſygnes conuenyent for the ſanguynes are: Taurus / Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go and Capricornus. For the cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rycke / Cancer / Scorpio &amp; Piſces For the melancolycke / Libra &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarius. For the flegmarycke: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Sagittarius. Leo is an euyll Sygne to let bloud in. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore / Age is to be conſydred
<pb facs="tcp:23738:23"/> alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> quarter of the Mone is apte for yonge age / the ſeconde for myddle age / the third &amp; fourth for olde age.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="observation">
            <head>¶ An obſeruation for Phiſycke.</head>
            <p>Whan the Moone is in ſygnes that be hote / than is the power at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractyue by heate &amp; drought / whan it is in erthy / than is the power at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tractyue: whan it is in ayrie ſygnes than is the powre digeſtyue.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London in the Olde Bayly in Sayntpoulchres paryſſh by Rychard Lant / for Rychard Grafton.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priuilegio ad imprimendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ This Pronoſtication is to be ſold at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weſt dore of Paules by wyllyam Telotſon.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23738:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
